Guide to the Miscellaneous Historical Maps Collection, circa 1558-1989 (bulk 1820-1945)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Miscellaneous Historical Maps Collection
circa 1558-1989
1820-1945
Approximately 115 maps (3 boxes, 1 framed item)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Collection of maps, charts, atlas pages, and illustrations depicting various regions of the globe ranging from the 16th to 20th centuries, with a particular focus on the United States and New York.
Scope and Content Note
Collection of maps, charts, atlas pages, and illustrations depicting various regions of the globe ranging from the 16th to 20th centuries, with a particular focus on the United States and New York.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Atlas Collection
Breed Collection of Maps, Documents, and Prints
Edward Lasker Collection of Atlases and Maps
Richmond John Rathbone Collection of Rare Maps
Subject Headings
Names:
Kitchin, Thomas, 1719-1784; Langenes, Barent; Lewis, Samuel, 1753 or 1754-1822; Moll, Herman, -1732; Moore, Raymond C. (Raymond Cecil), 1892-1974; Seutter, Matthäus, 1678-1757; Warren, G. K. (Gouverneur Kemble), 1830-1882
Places:
Europe--Maps; Great Britain--Maps; Germany--Maps; Italy--Maps; North America--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; North America--Maps; United States—History—Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--Maps
Document Types:
Maps; Manuscripts (documents); Prints (visual works)
VCL Categories:
Local History; Maps
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, November 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of various donors.
Arrangement
The maps are organized into series roughly by geographic area. There is considerable overlap between the sub-series, though, so careful browsing is required to complete a thorough search of the collection.
Within each series, maps are arranged in alphabetical order by creator or title.
Series List
- EUROPE
- EUROPE — GERMANY
- EUROPE — GREAT BRITAIN
- EUROPE — ITALY
- EUROPE — NETHERLANDS
- JAPAN
- MISCELLANEOUS
- NEAR EAST
- NORTH AMERICA
- NORTH AMERICA — MEXICO
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — CIVIL WAR MAPS
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — KANSAS
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — LOUISIANA
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — MASSACHUSETTS
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — MINNESOTA
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — NEW YORK
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — NEW YORK — DUTCHESS COUNTY AND POUGHKEEPSIE
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — PENNSYLVANIA
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — VIRGINIA
- NORTH AMERICA — UNITED STATES — WASHINGTON, D.C.
- WORLD
Container List
- EUROPE
  - Aitchison, R. T., "A Chart of the History of Printing in Europe,", undated; [2 copies] (M004 Ai91) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Kitchin, Thomas, "Poland with its Disimember'd Provinces,", 1784; [17x25 x 20.5] (M438 K648) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Munster, Sebastian, "Moderna Europae Descripto,", circa 1558 (Framed Storage 1.1)
  - Unidentified map of Europe, undated; [Several sheets printed on clear plastic] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- EUROPE - GERMANY
  - "Plan of Dresden, Capital of Saxony, the late Residence of the King of Poland, Elector of Saxony," Vincent Sculp., undated; [11.5 x 18.75 in] (Box 2)
- EUROPE - GREAT BRITAIN
  - "Bacon's New Map of London," London: G. W. Bacon & Co., circa 1900; (M421 B133) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - L'Ecosse Par le S. Robert de Vangondy Geographie ord?du Roi, de S.M.Pol? Duc de Lorr? Etde Bar, et de la Societe' royale de Nancy. 1762, undated; [15.75 x 10.75 in] (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "'Geographia' Map of England and Wales - Pictorial Plan of London,", 1923 (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Hartforde Shire,", undated; [5.5 x 3.5 in] (Box 2)
  - "Hertford From the Ordinance Survey" and "Report on the Borough of Hertford," [pages 239-242], undated; [8.5 x 13.75 in; 2 leaves] (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "Hertfordiae Comitatus A. Cat: tifuclanis olim Inhabitatus,", undated; [16.5 x 13.25 in] (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "Hertfordshire" [information on Hertfordshire and color map], undated; [11.5 x 16 in] (Dewey no. 942.58 C839?) (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "Hertfordshire," drawn and engraved for Lewis's Topographical Dictionary, undated; [12.5 x 9.75 in] (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - Jack, E. M., Brigadier, "Ordnance Survey Map of Roman Britain, Second Edition,", 1928; (M4201 G792) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - James, Major General Sir Henry, "Ancient Map of Great Britain (1870),", undated; [Facsimile] (M4203 G79) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - [Kent, Essex, Middlesex, Scotland, Buckinghamshire, West Riding of Yorkshire, Warwickshire, Lancashire] "…reproduced from John Norden’s map engraved by William Kip for Camden's 'Brittania' 1610,", undated; [16.75 x 15; 8 maps] (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - London, undated; (Dewey no. 973.2 B81) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - "Map of Jewish East London,", 1899; [24.5 x 18.75 in] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Map of the London General Bus Routes,", 1923 Nov; [17.5 x 14 in] (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "The Map of Great Britain (The Gough Map), circa 1360" (Reproduction from the collection of the Bodleain Library), [1958?]; (Dewey no. F 912.42 M322) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - [A Map of Great Britain and Surrounding Waters] "Sold by Herman Moll and by Iohn King at the Globe in the Poultrey near Stocks Market,", undated (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "A New and Exact Plan of the Cities of London and Westminster…1756,", 1989 Sep; [Facsimile] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "The North and East Ridings of Yorkshire" by John Speede, undated (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Walker, Emery, "The City of London Showing the Wards and Liberties as Described by Stow, c. 1600," with cover page of "The Pictorial Plan of London,", undated; [item removed from Survey of London by Stow, with original call number 942.1 St72] (M421 W15) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- EUROPE - ITALY
  - "Porto di Villafranca,", undated (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Seutter, Matthaus, "Nova Et Exactissima Italiae, Sardinia et Corsica…,", undated (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- EUROPE - NETHERLANDS
  - Sensex, Ion, "The VII United Provinces…dedicated to Elihu Yale Esq…,", 1709 (Map Case - Drawer 19)
- JAPAN
  - "Geological Maps of Japanese Empire" and "Depths of the Adjacent Seas of Japan" by the Hydrographic Department, 1926; [5 items] (M052 J27) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Map Showing the Depression and Upheaval of the Ground Produced at Kwato Districsts After the Great Earthquake of Sept. 1st, 1923,", undated; (M52 P19) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- MISCELLANEOUS MAPS
  - Langenes, Barent, "Eyland Chios" (probably from the "Caert Thresoor"), [1598?]; [4 x 6 in; mounted to 10 x 7.5 in] (Box 2)
  - Langenes, Barent, "Zante Insula" (probably from the "Caert Thresoor"), [1598?]; [4 x 6 in; mounted to 10 x 7.5 in] (Box 2)
  - Langenes, Barent, "Eyland Van Sancta Helena" (probably from the "Caert Thresoor"), [1598?]; [4 x 6 in; mounted to 10 x 7.5 in] (Box 2)
- NEAR EAST
  - "Map Shewing the Marches of Alexander" published by John Murray, undated; (M038 G915) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- NORTH AMERICA
  - "A Chart of the Discoveries and Route of the Northern Land Expedition Under the Command of Captain Franklin, R. N.,", [1923?] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "A copy of the map of 'that Province' in America made…,", undated; [extracted from Vol. 1, p. 456; 1 original, 2 photocopies] (Dewey no. 973.2 B81) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Cyprian Southack a New Chart of the English Empire in North America…1717,", 1942; [Facsimile; 4 items] (Dewey no. F 912.7 So87) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Glacial Map of North America,", 1945; [in 2 parts] (M007 N215 1) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - Lewis and Clark, "A Map of Lewis and Clark's Track Across the Western Portion of North America…,", 1804-1806; (M078 C549) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Seutter, Matthaus, "Recens Edita totius Novi Belgii in America Septentrionali fiti, delineation cura et fumtibus...,", undated; [17.5 x 15.5] (Box 3 (Oversize))
- NORTH AMERICA - MEXICO
  - "Battles of Mexico. Survey of the Line of Operations of the U.S. Army under the command of Major General Winfield Scott, on the 19th and 20th of August and the 8th, 12th, and 13th of September, 1847," drawn by Captain McClellan, U.S. Engineer Bureau, circa 1847; (M725 Un35) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Chatelain, Henri, "Description, situation, & vue de la Ville de Mexique...", undated (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Pourtraict et description del la grande cite de temistitan, 1397,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Siege of Vera Cruz by the U.S. Troops Under Major General Scott, March 1847," drawn by Captain McClellan, U.S. Engineer Bureau, circa 1847; (M726 Un35) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES
  - "Boston and New England via Poughkeepsie Bridge Crossing to the Coal Fields, The West and Southwest,", circa 1872 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Carte de la Campagne en Virgnie du Major Général Mis. de la Fayette ou fetrouvent les Campes et marches ainsy que ceux du Lieutent. Général Lord Cornwallis en 1781,", 1961; [Facsimile; 4 items] (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - "A Charter of King James His River in Virginia," from "Maps from The Genesis of the United States" by A. Brown, undated; [1 original, 1 photocopy] (Dewey no. 973.2 B81) (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - Fremont, John Charles, "Profile of the Traveling Route from the South Pass of the Rocky Mountains to the Bay of San Francisco; Map of the Oregon and Upper California from the Surveys of John Charles Fremont…,", 1848; (Dewey no. 912.795 P92) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - "The Herrman Map of Virginia and Maryland, London, 1673,", 1941; [Facsimile; 4 items] (M755 H436) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Map Showing Indian Reservations Within the Limit of the United States,", 1903-1904 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Map Showing The Relation of New England and the Iron Ore Fields of the East to the Coal Regions of Pennsylvania by the Poughkeepsie Bridge Route…,", undated (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Route of the Expedition from Isle de la Crosse to Fort Providence, in 1819 and 1820,", circa 1820; [9.25 x 20 in] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Route of the Expedition from York Factory to Cumberland House and the Summer & Winter Tracks from thence to Isle de la Crosse, in 1819 and 1820,", circa 1820; [22.5 x 9.75 in] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Stewart, Alexander, "A Map of the Seneca Villages and the Jesuit and French Contacts 1615-1708,", 1931; [20.5 x 17.5; 2 copies, 4 items] (Dewey no. 974.789 St4) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "The United States According to the Definitive Treaty of Peace Signed at Paris, Sept. 3, 1783,", undated; [19 x 18.5, cloth mounted] (M73 M22) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - U.S. Department of the Interior, "Map of the United States Showing Principal Explorers and Early Roads and Highways…,", 1908; (Dewey no. 912.731 Un3) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Warren, BVT Major General G. K., "Map of Nebraska and Dakota and Portions of the States and Territories Bordering Thereon…,", 1867; (Dewey no. 912.782 W25) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - Zuniga, "The Draught of St Georges Fort," from "Maps from The Genesis of the United States" by A. Brown, undated; [1 original, 1 photocopy] (Dewey no. 973.2 B81) (Box 3 (Oversize))
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - CIVIL WAR MAPS
  - Duval, P. S. and Son, "Map of the Seat of the War" and "Seat of the War in the West,", 1861; [2 items] (M075 D956) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Phelps and Watson's Historical and Military Map of the Border and Southern States, 1862; (M075 P511) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - "The Seat of the War; A Bird's Eye View of Virginia, Maryland, Delaware and the District of Columbia,", 1861; (M075 Sch1) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - Smith, W. E., "Battlefield of Chattanooga,", 1863; (M737 Un25) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - U.S. Coast Survey Office, "Map Showing the Operations of the National Forces under the Command of Maj. Gen. W. T. Sherman,", 1864; (M737 Un3) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - U.S. War Department, "Map Illustrating the Siege of Atlanta, Georgia,", 1864; (M737 Un32) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - U.S. War Department, Engineer Bureau, "Map Showing Route of Marches of the Army of Gen. W. T. Sherman from Atlanta to Boldsboro, NC,", 1864; [19 x 13 in] (M737 Un33) (Box 3 (Oversize))
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - KANSAS
  - Landes, Kenneth, "Oil and Gas Fields of Kansas,", 1932; (M781 K13) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - Moore, Raymond, "Contour Map Showing Topography of Pre-Cambrian Surface Underlying Eastern Two-Thirds of Kansas,", 1935; (Dewey no. 557.81 K137) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Moore, Raymond, "Geological Map of Kansas,", 1935; (Dewey no. 557.81 K1376) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Moore, Raymond, "Geological Map of Kansas, Northwestern Kansas,", 1935; (Dewey no. 557.81 K1373) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Moore, Raymond, "Geological Map of Kansas, Southwestern Kansas,", 1935; (Dewey no. 557.81 K1374) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Moore, Raymond, "The Surface Features of Kansas,", 1935; (Dewey no. 557.81 K1375) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - LOUISIANA
  - Franquelin, Louis, "Carte de la Louisiane…1684,", undated; [Facsimile] (Dewey no. 912.763 F85) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - MASSACHUSETTS
  - "A Geological Map of Massachusetts,", 1832 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Map of the Metropolitan District of Boston Showing Local Public Reservations…,", 1921; (M7446 B65) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - "Massachusetts," published by Dorr. Howland & Co., Worcester, 1839; [13.25 x 8.5 in] (Box 3 (Oversize))
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - MINNESOTA
  - Brower, J. V., "Detailed Hydrographic Chart of the Ultimate Source of the Mississippi River,", 1891; (Dewey no. 912.77 B8) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Geological Map of the State of Minnesota,", 1932; (M776 M66 (1)) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - NEW YORK
  - Burr, David, "Map of the County of Oswego,", 1829; (M74767 B94) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Lewis, Samuel, "The State of New York, Compiled from the best Authorities…,", 1795 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Manor Reselaerwick by Bleeker, 1767; (M74741 B615) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "A Plan of the City of New York,", 1834; [Facsimile; 18 x 22.5] (M7471 L99) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Pictorial New York,", 1855; (Dewey no. 912.747 P58) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - "The Rand-McNally Vest Pocket Map of New York City,", 1911; (M7471 R16) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Stevens, B. F., "British Headquarter Map of New York and Environs, 1782,", undated; [Facsimile, 3 sheets (incomplete set); 15x25 x 22.5] (M7471 G798) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - NEW YORK - DUTCHESS COUNTY AND POUGHKEEPSIE
  - Beers, F.W., "Town of Poughkeepsie" [from Atlas of New York and Vicinity], 1867; [13.5 x 16.5 in, mounted] (Dewey no. F 912.747 B39) (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "Dutchess County Soil Survey Map,", 1907; (Dewey no. 747.3 M77) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - "Fenner's Map On Trail with P.V. Burgh Aug, 1809...Showing some land later including in the Vassar Campus,", undated; [2 maps; positive and negative photostats] (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Great Nine Partners Patent, N.Y. Dutchess Co.,", undated; [Photostatic copy] (Dewey no. 747.3 G798) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "A Map of Dutchess County, New York from Actual Surveys," John E. Gillette, Publisher, Philadelphia, 1858; [Folded cloth map; 9.75 x 10.5 in (folded); 59 x 63 in (unfolded)] (Box 1)
  - "Map of Dutchess Co. New York from actual surveys. John Gillette, Publisher, 517, 519, 521, Minor Str. Philadelphia,", 1858; [Part 1 of 2] (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Map of Dutchess Co. New York from actual surveys. John Gillette, Publisher, 517, 519, 521, Minor Str. Philadelphia,", 1858; [Part 2 of 2] (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "A Map of the Lands of Poughkeepsie…1770,", undated; [Photocopy] (M747.33 C644) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - Map of Poughkeepsie, circa 1852; (M747.33 Si14) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - "Map of the City of Poughkeepsie,", 1876 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Map of the Town of Poughkeepsie, by Livingston, 1790,", undated; [12.75 x 18.5; photostatic copy] (Dewey no. 747.33 L762) (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - "A Map of the Incorporated Village of Poughkeepsie, 1834,", undated; [3 items; positive and negative photostats] (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Map Supplement to the Dutchess County Guide of the American Guide Series,", 1938 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Plan of Dutchess Co.,", 1867; [2 copies] (Dewey no. 747.3 B392) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Plan of the City of Poughkeepsie,", 1867; (Dewey no. 747.3 B392) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Poughkeepsie, circa 1920; (M747.33 C76) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - "Poughkeepsie, Upper Red Hook / Map of Unionvale Township,", 1876 (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - "Second and Corrected Copy of the Lands Belonging to the Estate of Esther Emily Parker, Poughkeepsie,", undated; [Photocopy] (Map Case - Drawer 18)
  - "Town of Poughkeepsie,", 1867; (Dewey no. 747.3 B392) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - PENNSYLVANIA
  - Stose, George W. and O. A. Ljungstedt, "Geographic Map of Pennsylvania Department of Internal Affairs…,", 1931; (M748 P38) (Map Case - Drawer 18)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - VIRGINIA
  - Nelson, Wilbur, "Geological Map of Virginia,", 1928; (M755 V81) (Map Case - Drawer 17)
  - Zuniga, Chart of Virigina, "sent from London, England, 10th Sept., 1608,", undated; [16x5 x 19; opp. p. 184; 1 original and 2 copies] (Dewey no. 973.2 B81) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
- NORTH AMERICA - UNITED STATES - WASHINGTON, D.C.
  - "L'Enfant's Plan for Washington D.C.; Printed by the United States Coast and Geodetic Survey Office, 1887,", undated; [Facsimile] (Dewey no. F 912.753 L52) (Map Case - Drawer 19)
- WORLD
  - "The Cassini World Map of 1696,", undated; [Facsimile] (Map Case - Drawer 19)
  - Leardo Map of the World, undated; (Dewey no. 912 L478) (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Orbis Terrarum,", undated (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - "Typus Orbis Terrarum,", undated; [Photostat of map missing from Special Collections copy of Hakluyt, Richard Principall (Hairgalions), London, 1587] (Map Case - Drawer 6)
  - World Map (Hispanic Society of America), 1912; (Dewey no. F 860.6 H62) (Map Case - Drawer 19)